Guide to the collection of Brooklyn, N.Y., Civil War relief associations records, ephemera and other material ARC.245
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 3: Brooklyn and Long Island Fair, circa 1799-1866, 1964; 2.33 Linear Feet
  - Events: Admission Tickets, 1863-1864 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    The folder includes some admission tickets to events other than the Brooklyn and Long Island Fair, including to other events in Brooklyn and to other relief initiatives.
  - Bills of Fare, 1863-1864 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Credit Receipts and Tokens, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Printed Forms and Documents, circa 1864 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - The Drum Beat, daily newspaper (photocopies), 1864 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The Drum Beat (originals; restricted), 1864 (Box 8, Folder -)
    Because of the fragile state of these documents, access to these originals is restricted and requires approval of the Director. Researchers are directed to the photocopies in box 3 or additional bound copies in box 6.
  - The Drum Beat (originals; bound), Feb. 22-Mar. 5, 1864 (Box 6, Folder -)
  - Walter T. Hatch Account Book for The Drum Beat, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Clippings (unbound scrapbook), 1864 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Clippings (loose), 1864 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Clippings (oversize), 1864 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Includes pages with images from Frank Leslie's Illustrated, New York Illustrated, and Harper's Weekly.
  - Poetry: Manuscript by Marion Grey The Mission of the Hour, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    This item was intended to be read at the Fair's opening ceremony, but such a ceremony was not conducted.
  - Poetry: Print Matter, circa 1864 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Poetry: Print Matter (oversize), circa 1864 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    The printing plate for the document in this folder is also in the collection, in box 12.
  - Stereotype Printing Plate, 1863 (Box 12, Item 1)
    This plate is associated with the oversize poetry print matter in box 7.
  - Advertising Leaflets for Commercial Products, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Exhibits: Mexican War Era Correspondence, 1846-1847 (Box 3, Drawer 26)
    These documents are in Spanish.
  - Exhibits: Strand of George Washington's Hair, circa 1799 (Box 6, Item 3)
  - Exhibits: Samples of Broadcloth Used for Henry Clay Suit, 1844 (Box 6, Item 4)
  - Exhibits: The Rights of the Legal Voter, and the Law and the Penalty of Fraudulent Voting (Henry Clay campaign material), 1844 (Box 6, Item 5)
  - Exhibits: Fragment of the Ellsworth (?) Flag, undated (Box 6, Item 6)
  - Exhibits: Scrapbook of Confederate Song Lyrics, 1861-circa 1864 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Exhibits: Album of Autographs Collected by Gertrude Lefferts Vanderbilt, circa 1830-1897 (Box 9, Item 1)
    The album includes a page from James Fenimore Cooper's manuscript of Water-Witch, Chapter 6 (circa 1830), and related correspondence from Susan Fenimore Cooper (1886). There is also a page from Washington Irving's manuscript of The Life of George Washington, Volume 4 (circa 1858). Other contributors, represented by an autographed note or poem, are: Lewis Agassiz, George Bancroft, Henry Ward Beecher, George H. Boker, William Cullen Bryant, Richard Henry Dana, Ralph Waldo Emerson, Edward Everett, James T. Fields, Fitz Greene Halleck, Nathaniel Hawthorne, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Henry W. Longfellow, James Russell Lowell, Donald G. Mitchell, Wendell Phillips, Epes Sargent, Jared Sparks, Charles Sprague, Edmond C. Stedman, Richard Henry Stoddard, Charles Sumner, Bayard Taylor, George Ticknor, J.T. Trowbridge, John G. Whittier, and Nathaniel P. Willis.
  - Miscellaneous Ephemera, circa 1864 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Long Island Historical Society, 1864-1866, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Series 4: Lincoln Monument Fund, 1865-1868; 0.42 Linear Feet
  This series contains materials from the fund established by the War Fund Committee to raise money for a statue in honor of Abraham Lincoln following his assassination in 1865. The correspondence largely relates to individual donations. Additional material regarding donations is contained in the documentation of one dollar subscriptions solicited from individuals at their places of employment. These records were used to compile an alphabetical index of contributors, contained in a bound ledger also found in the series. The contract with H. K. Brown, sculptor of the Lincoln statue, is in the series and includes signed statements noting dates and amounts of payment received.
  The series has no particular arrangement.
  - Correspondence, 1865-1867 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - H.K. Brown, Sculptor, Contract and Correspondence, 1866-1868 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Subscription Books, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Subscription Lists (4 folders), 1865 (Box 4, Folder 4-7)
  - Subscription Lists, Navy Yard, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Cash Book, 1865-1868 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - List of Contributors, circa 1865 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Mourning Tracts, circa 1865 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Series 5: Other Relief Organizations and Events, 1861-1867; 0.42 Linear Feet
  This series contains materials relating to various relief organizations as well as events to raise money on their behalf, primarily to assist the war effort. The series includes information concerning the Brooklyn bureau of the American Freedmen's Friend Society, led by prominent African-Americans including James N. Gloucester and William J. Wilson. Other local organizations represented include the Brooklyn and Long Island Christian Commission and the records of a collection taken in Brooklyn in response to a fire in Portland, Maine. Several other cities' Fairs are represented in the series, including newspapers printed for the Fairs at Boston, Indianapolis, New York City, Philadelphia, and Springfield, Mass. There is a small amount of information relating to the U.S. Sanitary Commission, including an overview of its operations as presented at a statistical conference in Berlin in 1863, among other documents.
  The series is arranged with other Fairs followed by other organizations, alphabetical by city and by organization name, respectively.
  - Army Relief Bazaar (Albany), 1863-1864 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - National Sailors' Fair (Boston): Boatswain's Whistle, 1864 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Northern Ohio Sanitary Fair (Cleveland): Sanitary Fair Gazette, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Sanitary Fair (Dutchess County and Poughkeepsie), 1864 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - State Sanitary Fair (Indianapolis): Sanitary Fair Bulletin, 1864 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Metropolitan Fair (New York City), 1864 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Metropolitan Fair (New York City): Spirit of the Fair, 1864 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Great Central Fair (Philadelphia), 1864 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Great Central Fair (Philadelphia): Our Daily Fare, 1864 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Mississippi Valley Sanitary Fair (St. Louis), 1864 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Other Fairs, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - American Freedmen's Friend Society (Brooklyn), circa 1864 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Brooklyn and Long Island Christian Commission, 1863-1864 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - General Soldiers' Aid Society (Connecticut), 1863 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Portland (Maine) Fire Relief Fund: Brooklyn Contributions (2 folders), 1866-1867 (Box 5, Folder 10, 11)
  - U.S Sanitary Commission (National), 1861-1864 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - U.S. Sanitary Commission (Philadelphia, Pittsburgh), 1863-1864 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Bound Copies of Fair Newspapers, 1864 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Includes complete runs of Spirit of the Fair (New York, April 5-23), Our Daily Fare (June 8-21, Philadelphia), Boatswain's Whistle (November 9-19, Boston), and Springfield (Mass.) Musket (December 20-23).
  - Ladies Southern Relief Association Benefit Pamphlets, 1867, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    One pamphlet from March 22nd 1867 for poetry recitations and other recitations at the Packer Collegiate Institute, and another undated pamphlet for a concert on March 27th at Plymouth Church.
  - Destitute Families of the Soldiers of Brooklyn Ball Flyer, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series 6: Ephemera and Miscellaneous, circa 1798-circa 1895; 0.25 Linear Feet
  This series contains a wide variety of materials principally concerning the Civil War or from the Civil War era. A small number of documents date from prior to the Civil War. It might be that some of the items were exhibited at the Brooklyn and Long Island Fair, but this is unknown. Civil War-related materials include poems; a manuscript by Capt. Samuel Whiting read to the Long Island Historical Society describing his experiences at Fort Sumter in 1861 and as U.S. Consul to the Bahamas afterward; printed remarks at the presentation of a flag to the 26th Regiment, U.S. Colored Troops (raised in New York by the Union League Club); a printed solicitation by Edward Everett on behalf of Lieut. Worden of the ship "Monitor"; a sheet of tax notes from the city of Charleston, S.C.; Confederate regiment documents such as pay accounts and quartermaster requisitions; and several other documents.
  Documents dating from the Civil War era include materials relating to the 1864 Presidential campaign, including the first number of The World, a newspaper supporting McClellan, covering the Democratic National Convention; orders and other documents concerning two New York State National Guard regiments, the 13th and the 26th (these documents do not relate to the regiments' service in the war); proposed alphabets for the blind (with raised lettering); commercial advertisements; and some items printed in response to Lincoln's assassination. The advertisements include two broadsheets, one documenting 1864 financial and other data for all fire insurance companies doing business in New York State and the second soliciting the general public to purchase tax-exempt U.S. government bonds. A Bradstreet's Commercial Reports circa 1865 for the New England states and eastern Canada is in the series, used in part as a scrapbook for poems.
  Some of the material throughout the series relates to local Brooklyn or New York organizations, such as the articles of association for the Sewing Society of the Summerfield Methodist Episcopal Church in Brooklyn. These local connections are highlighted with notes in the container list below.
  The series opens with a folder of pre-Civil War period material, followed by material with a Civil War connection, then material dating from the Civil War period but not directly concerning the war itself.
  - Pre-Civil War: Miscellany, circa 1798-1858 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Includes a poem written for the Fair of the Mariners' Family Industrial Society, Port of New-York (1847) and other verses; two programs for the N.Y. Fire Department Annual Ball (1848, 1850); and a newspaper clipping of Henry Ward Beecher's sermon "Men's excuses for not becoming Christians" (1858).
  - Civil War: Poems, 1862-1864 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Civil War: Poems (Scrapbook) / Bradstreet's Commercial Reports, 1861-1864 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    The first several pages of a Bradstreet's Commercial Reports were used as a scrapbook for Civil War-related poems, obscuring most pages with Connecticut business reports. However, the bulk of the reports overall were not obscured. These concern businesses in the other New England states and in Eastern Canada.
  - Civil War: Poem (Clipping from Harper's Weekly), 1864 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Civil War: Capt. Samuel Whiting Manuscript, 1863 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Civil War: Field of Shiloh Map, circa 1862 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Civil War: Union States Miscellany, 1861-1865 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Includes broadside of "Mr. Jay's address on presenting the colours prepared by the ladies of New York to the second coloured regiment [26th Regiment, USCT] raised by the Union League Club"; a copy of General Orders No. 8 concerrning the 159th NY Regiment; an appeal by Edward Everett on behalf of Lieut. Worden of the "Monitor," among other items.
  - Civil War: Union States Miscellany (oversize), circa 1865 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Includes two broadsheets: Description of events at the presentation of the flag of the 149th NY Regiment to the Onondaga Historical Association and a description of the annual meeting of the State Historical Society of Wisconsin referring to Civil War collections.
  - Civil War: Confederate State Miscellany, 1861-1865 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    Includes a swatch of cloth said to be from the flag at Fort Pulaski, supply requisitions for troops, caricatures of Jefferson Davis, and other documents.
  - Civil War: Charleston, S.C., Tax Notes, 1862 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Civil War Era: Lincoln Assassination, 1865 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Civil War Era: 13th Regiment, NY National Guard, 1861-1864 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Civil War Era: 23rd Regiment, NY National Guard, 1863-1864 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Civil War Era: Politics and Elections, 1862-1864 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Civil War Era: The World, No. 1, Campaign Edition, 1864 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Civil War Era: United States Mutual Protection Homestead Company, circa 1865 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    One item moved to the following folder to be stored in the oversize box.
  - Civil War Era: Commercial Advertisements, circa 1865 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Includes broadsheet produced by Continental Fire Insurance Company, with 1864 financial and other data for all fire insurance companies doing business in New York State (1865), and a broadsheet advertising sales of tax-exempt U.S. government bonds to the general public.
  - Civil War Era: Proposed Alphabet for the Blind, 1863 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Civil War Era: Miscellany, 1863-circa 1865 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    Includes articles of association of the Summerfield Methodist Episcopal Church (Brooklyn) Sewing Society (1861); carte-de-visite of Church of the Holy Trinity (by Barnum); Suffolk County Sabbath School Association financial report (1864-65); solicitation from the N.Y. Association for the Advancement of Science and Art" (1865); Beck Memorial solicitation, Albany Academy (1863); resolutions concerning sale of U.S. mineral lands (1864); circular of Fitchburg (Mass.) Anti-Tobacco Tract Depository (circa 1865).
  - Image of 14th Regiment "Mascot" John W. Evans, 1861 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Front page of "The Old Guard" with features regarding the 14th Regiment of Brooklyn, June 1895 (Box OS-40)
  - Prisoners of the 14th Regiment March Poster (Box 5, Folder 28)